<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<doc>
    <title>Authorization</title>
    <paragraph>
        Within some parts of Adaptive Framework, a decision has to be made on 
        whether to permit an operation or not. These decisions may invoke  
        external logic to execute through a process collectively known as  
        <literal>Authorization</literal>. For instance, when a client wishes to 
        update the property of an object, or request that a new extension be 
        loaded, or a service to be stopped, we invoke Authorization code, when 
        such code is available. This gives administrators the ability to plug 
        in their own authorization logic, and to make decisions based on 
        business policy.
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph>
        How Adaptive Framework locates the appropriate Authorization policy to 
        invoke somewhat depends upon the operation being performed. Some 
        authorization logic can be specified at the Application level, which 
        will apply to all decisions. Other authorization logic may be declared  
        on just a particular service, so that its decisions will only apply to 
        operations pertaining to an adaptor being used.
    </paragraph>
    <paragraph>
        An authorization decision in Adaptive Framework borrows heavily from 
        the way <literal>XACML</literal> defines it: Can a <literal>Subject</literal>
        perform a particular <literal>Action</literal> on a particular 
        <literal>Resource</literal> within a given <literal>Environment</literal>?         
        Authorization scripts are provided access to each of these parts 
        in order to render a decision.
    </paragraph>
    <image 
        src="images/AuthorizationDiagram.svg" 
        description="Authorization Diagram" 
        caption="Diagram illustrating an authorization process" 
    />
    <paragraph>
        The previous diagram illustrates the steps that are taken from the start
        of a client request to the response that is returned. The 
        <literal>Authentication</literal> in steps (2) and (3) are optional, but
        they are steps that are often taken when an un-verified client wishes to
        make a request for data. The role of Adaptive Framework does not really
        start until step (5), when all of the subject information has been
        gathered and that will be needed in order to make an authorization
        decision.
    </paragraph>
</doc>