<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<doc>
    <title>Provisioning</title>
    <paragraph>
        When Adaptive Objects are committed to an adapter store, a record of 
        the event, may optionally be recorded by a <literal>Journal 
        Adapter</literal> in order to maintain a chronological ordering of 
        events, which may be used to notify external clients. 
        <literal>Provisioning</literal> describes the process by which Adaptive 
        Objects may be synchronized between an adapter and one or more clients, 
        or <literal>Provisioning Peers</literal>.
    </paragraph>  
    <section>
        <title>Journal</title>
        <paragraph>
            Any adapter may be configured with an optional 
            <literal>journalAdapterId</literal>, which references an adapter 
            that supports the Journaling of object events. When an object is
            modified through the adapter interface methods (add, delete, modify,
            replace, update), a <literal>Journal Entry</literal> of the event is 
            created and sent to the provided Journal Adapter. This Journal
            Entry contains information about the event, including the Request
            and Source information about the entry. The Journal Entry is added
            to an event queue, and each entry is referenced by a 
            <literal>Journal Cursor</literal>. Cursors are used to uniquely 
            identify an Journal Entry and entries may be fetched from the queue 
            in chronological order, using these chain of cursors. The cursors
            may be used by both the Provisioning Peer and Journal Adapter to
            replay a series of events that have occurred from any range within
            the Journal.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            A Journal Entry is produced for the Journal Adapter, by a single 
            Provisioning Peer. The Journal Entry may then be consumed by one or 
            more Provisioning Peers. The Journal Interface routines provide all
            of the necessary functions to provision in and out of the Journal.
            For more details on the Journal interface functions, see 
            <link src="/Reference/Function/journal">Journal</link>.
        </paragraph> 
        <paragraph>
            A <literal>Producer</literal> is anything that produces an event 
            that will be journaled. In the following diagram, we illustrate how
            a Provisioning Peer may produce an event simply by calling the
            <literal>add_object()</literal> routine to an adapter. The adapter, 
            in turn, is configured with a Journal Adapter, which knows to take
            the object and add it to its queue of Journal Entries.
        </paragraph>           
        <image 
            src="images/ProvisioningProducer.svg" 
            description="Provisioning Producer creates an object to be journaled." 
            caption="Provisioning Producer creates an object to be journaled." 
        />
        <paragraph>
            By contrast, an <literal>Consumer</literal> is a client that 
            consumes events from the Journal. These clients interact directly 
            with the Journal Adapter itself by calling Journal routines that 
            can fetch the first event, or an event after a positional cursor. 
            When consumed, the event is removed from the Journal through a 
            request to mark it consumed.
        </paragraph>
        <image 
            src="images/ProvisioningConsumer.svg" 
            description="Provisioning Consumer consumes an object from the Journal." 
            caption="Provisioning Consumer consumes an object from the Journal."
        />
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Provisioning Peers</title>
        <paragraph>
            A Provisioning Peer is a client, external to the Journal, which 
            may produce and/or consume Journal Entries. Provisioning Peers are 
            uniquely identified by a <literal>peerId</literal>, which 
            associates a peer with the following Provisioning Peer object 
            properties:
        </paragraph>
        <object-type-table objectTypeId="_AdaptiveProvisioningPeer_" />                 
        <paragraph>
            When Provisioning Peers call journal functions, the peerId that 
            is specified by the peering client, should be authenticated and 
            authorized in order to deliver the appropriate data to the 
            Provisioning Peer. While anyone can produce events to be journaled, 
            or consume events from a Journal, the concept of a Provisioning 
            Peer allows you to pre-define and centrally-manage producers and 
            consumers in order to support filters, maintain cursors, and 
            additional information about the peer. Additionally, when a 
            Provisioning Peer produces an event, the peerId should be provided 
            in order to avoid event loopback situations, where a consumer could 
            consume the very event it produced.
        </paragraph>        
    </section>
</doc>